Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York; Records apap064
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, NY Records
1934-1988
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, NY
apap064
2.3 cubic ft.
The Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York, (BPW) was founded in 1934 with 22 charter members as a chapter of the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, Inc. (founded in 1919) and a member of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc. The objectives of the club, according to its by-laws, were "To elevate the standards for women in business and in the professions; To promote the interests of business and professional women; To bring about a spirit of cooperation among business and professional women of the United States; [and] To extend opportunities to business and professional women through education along lines of industrial, scientific, and vocational activities."
Access
Access to these records is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York, on May 11, 1988.
Biographical History
The Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York, (BPW) was founded in 1934 with 22 charter members as a chapter of the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, Inc. (founded in 1919) and a member of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc. The objectives of the club, according to its by-laws, were "To elevate the standards for women in business and in the professions; To promote the interests of business and professional women; To bring about a spirit of cooperation among business and professional women of the United States; [and] To extend opportunities to business and professional women through education along lines of industrial, scientific, and vocational activities."
The officers of the club (a president, a vice-president, a recording secretary, a corresponding secretary and a treasurer) constituted the Executive Committee, which ran the affairs of the club.
BPW was especially interested in attaining its goals through legislation concerned broadly with women's rights rather than specifically with businesswomen's rights. One of their first concerns was to change the law so women would be allowed to serve on juries. After winning that battle in 1939, the BPW began a new drive to make participation on juries mandatory for women by deleting a section of the 1939 law that automatically exempted women from sitting on a jury. This law was important to them because they wanted to achieve equal responsibilities as well as equal rights for women. During the 1930s and 1940s the BPW worked for the passage of the equal rights amendment. They also opposed a law that would set a lower minimum wage for women, and they pushed for equal pay for equal work. At the end of World War II, the BPW campaigned for the retention of the women's units as parts of the military, and they advocated participation in the United Nations as a means to peaceful settlement of international disputes. In the 1950s, they sponsored female foreign exchange students. Throughout its existence the BPW advocated women attaining political office as a way to help change laws and saw the promotion of good public relations as a means of changing public opinion.
Scope and Contents
The newspaper clippings, though not in perfect chronological order, contain the most information about the early years of the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York. BPW was interested in having its ideas appear in the local newspapers, so the clippings file has much information no the concerns and also the activities of BPW. Another source for information on the club's early years is The Hustler, a monthly newsletter of BPW, but this is a small leaflet with little information. There are a few other series that cover the first years of the club, but they rarely contain much information. Some of the photographs cover these years. The rosters of members contain lists of members along with their addresses and occupations. The radio scripts from 1936 and 1938 are interesting items that show one public relations method the club used.
The clippings files for the 1970s and the 1980s are not as complete as the earlier news clippings because there are few clippings for any of these years. Citations make up the of the files, and these only give clues to the activities of the club. For the later years, the minutes of the board meetings and those for the general business meetings have much more information on the activities and the concerns of the club. Another interesting source is the award entries, which contain material the club entered into contests for best club of the year and best program.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series: Series 1- Constitution and By-Laws 1934-1982, Series 2- Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 1972-1985, Series 3- Business Meeting Minutes 1973-1985, Series 4- Financial Reports 1954-1985, Series 5- Award Entries 1981-1982, Series 6- Photographs 1935-1968, Series 7- News Clippings 1834-1987, Series 8- Publications 1938-1988, Series 9- Radio Scripts 1936-1938, Series 10- Rosters of Members 1934-1986.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Education; Business and Industry; Albany, New York; New York (State); Reports; Proposals; Summaries; Fliers; The Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York
- Constitution and By-Laws, 1934-1982; 1; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged Alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Records giving the organizational structure of the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York, as well as that of the state and national groups. Includes revisions of the by-laws (1979-80, 1982), a printed copy of the certificate of incorporation for the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, Inc. (1965), copies of the constitution of the BPW of Albany (1934), and maps and charts showing the district organization of BPW in New York State (1976).
  - By-Laws, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Constitution and By-Laws), Folder 1)
  - By-Laws and Brochures on the Organization of BPW, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Constitution and By-Laws), Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1965; 1967 (Box 3 (1-Constitution and By-Laws), Folder 3)
  - Constitution of Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, NY, 1934; 1954 (Box 4 (1-Constitution and By-Laws), Folder 4)
  - District Organization of BPW in New York state, Maps and Charts, 1976 (Box 5 (1-Constitution and By-Laws), Folder 5)
- Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1972-1985; 2; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Arranged Chronologically.
  Minutes of board meetings, including some pertinent memoranda and reports.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1972-1980 (Box 1 (2-Board of Directors Meeting Minutes), Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (2-Board of Directors Meeting Minutes), Folder 7)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 1 (2-Board of Directors Meeting Minutes), Folder 8)
- Business Meeting Minutes, 1973-1985; 3; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Minutes of the regular business meetings, which were the general meetings of the BPW.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 1 (3-Business Meeting Minutes), Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 1 (3-Business Meeting Minutes), Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (3-Business Meeting Minutes), Folder 11)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 1 (3-Business Meeting Minutes), Folder 12)
- Financial Reports, 1954-1985; 4; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Includes proposed budgets, Finance Committee reports, treasurer's reports, auditor's reports, and financial statements.
  - Reports, 1954 (Box 1 (4-Financial Reports), Folder 13)
  - Reports, 1973-1980 (Box 1 (4-Financial Reports), Folder 14)
  - Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 1 (4-Financial Reports), Folder 15)
- Award Entries, 1981-1982; 5; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Contains entries and supporting materials submitted to contests, including the contest for the program award for the best single program held by a local BPW club And the contest for the outstanding club of the year award for BPW clubs in New York state.
  - Entry Form, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 16)
  - Health Management Fairs, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 17)
  - Participation, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 18)
  - Public Relations, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 19)
  - Luncheon, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 20)
  - Exhibits, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 21)
  - Entry Form and Citation, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 22)
  - Participation, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 23)
  - Public Relations, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 24)
  - Evening Events, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 25)
  - Exhibits, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 26)
  - Contest Entry, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Award Entries), Folder 27)
- Photographs, 1935-1968; 6; 0.68 cubic ft.
  Photographs of club activities, officers, state and national levels, women in New York State government, Frances Vosburgh, Dorothy Titchner, and Margaret Barnard.
  - Barnard, Margaret, 1947-1961 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 28)
  - Barnard, Margaret, 1947-1961 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 29)
  - Members and Activities, 1949-1968 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 30)
  - Members and Activities, 1949-1968 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 31)
  - Members and Activities, 1949-1968 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 32)
  - Presidents and Officers, State and Local, 1935-1966 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 33)
  - Presidents and Officers, National, 1939; ca. 1940 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 34)
  - Titchner, Dorothy, 1956 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 35)
  - Vosburgh, Frances, 1966 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 36)
  - Women in Government, Harriman Administration, ca. 1950 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 37)
  - Women in Government, Rockefeller Administration, ca. 1960 (Box 1 (6-Photographs), Folder 38)
- News Clippings, 1934-1987; 7; 1 cubic ft.
  Extensive clippings fill on BPW members and on the activities of BPW to make its concerns known. Includes some award certificates and a few photographs.
  - News Clippings, 1934-1939 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1950-1954 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1955-1959 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1961-1962 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 6)
  - 1970-1980 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, 1980-1984; 1987 (Box 2 (7-News Clippings), Folder 8)
- Publications, 1938-1988; 8; 0.10 cubic ft.
  Includes The Hustler a monthly newsletter of BPW of Albany (1939-1971, with gaps), BPW...Action Line a monthly newsletter of BPW of Albany (1979-1988, with gaps), histories of BPW of Albany (1961-1968) and of New York State (1960), and other publications.
  - BPW Action Line (newsletter), 1979-1988 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Facts and Faces, 1919-1959, a history of the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, 1960 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 10)
  - Flyers for People Running for Offices in National BPW, ca. 1982 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 11)
  - History of the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, 1960-1968 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 12)
  - The Hustler, Newsletter, 1939-1971 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Our Town's Business, Pamphlet, 1938 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Programs and Announcements of Activities, 1940-1984 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 15)
  - Publications of BPW of New York State, 1956; 1980 (Box 2 (8-Publications), Folder 16)
- Radio Scripts, 1936-1938; 9; 0.10 cubic ft.
  The scripts for radio conversations presented over WABY by the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany to inform the public of BPW, its activities, and its concerns.
  - Radio Scripts, 1936; 1938 (Box 2 (9-Radio Scripts), Folder 18)
- Roster of Members, 1934-1986; 10; 1 cubic ft.
  Published roster's of members for individual years, but includes the roster of charter members which is a list of signatures of charter members.
  - Charter Members, ca. 1934 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 19)
  - Members, 1939-1950 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 20)
  - Members, 1951-1956 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 21)
  - Members, 1961-1969 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 22)
  - Members, 1970-1980 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 23)
  - Members, 1981-1986 (Box 2 (10-Roster of Members), Folder 24)